srt2smi : AxHatchet
KING: I accept this honor
for our lost ones,
whose deaths pave our path.
And for the 20 million
Negro men and women
motivated by dignity
and a disdain
for hopelessness.
This isn't right.
Corrie.
This ain't right.
CORETTA: What's that?
This necktie.
It's not right.
Well, it's not
a necktie, dear.
It's an ascot.
Yes, but generally
the same principles
should apply,
shouldn't they?
It's not right.
It's not right,
or you don't like it?
(SIGHS) I don't like
how this looks.
Looks distinguished
and debonair to me.
You know what I mean.
Like we're living
high on the hog.
Dressed like this
while folks back home
are... (SIGHS)
It's not right.
Wait till the brothers
back home see me like this.
They'll have a good laugh.
Let them laugh.
It's not a crime to be away
for a few days, Martin.
It's nice being away, huh?
Yeah. It really is.
Look here.
I'm gonna be a pastor
somewhere small.
College town.
(CHUCKLING)
Lead a little church.
Teach a class.
(SIGHS)
Maybe the occasional
speaking engagement.
And I'll pay
all the bills for us,
especially the mortgage
for our very own house.
Perfect.
You look handsome.
JAHN: Through it all,
Martin Luther King
has spoken of his dream.
One which we
and many other people
around the world share.
To this undeterred hero
for justice,
the Nobel Committee
of Oslo, Norway,
awards our 1964 Peace Prize.
(AUDIENCE APPLAUDING)
KING: I accept this honor
for our lost ones,
whose deaths pave our path.
I accept this honor for
the more than 20 million
American Negroes
who are motivated
by dignity.
Together we believe that
what the illusion
of supremacy has destroyed,
the truth of equality
can nourish.
GIRL 1: I promise you.
It ain't nothing
to be scared of.
It's quick. And the pastor
is right there next to you.
Yeah,
but the biggest thing is
getting your hair wet up.
I got my hair pressed
that same morning
and it was wasted
as soon as I hit the water.
I should have
worn a swim cap
like Mama said.
(CHILDREN LAUGHING)
GIRL 2: See,
I asked my mama
could she make my hair like
Coretta Scott King had hers
at the Washington March.
But she said
that was too grown.
Oh, I love her hair.
I heard she don't
even put rollers in it.
It's just like that.
But I studied it.
I know how she do it.
See, she parts
in the middle and then...
(SIGHS)
MAN: Annie Lee Cooper!
Get on up now.
I ain't got all day.
You work for Mr. Dunn
down at the rest home,
ain't that right?
Yes.
Wonder what old Dunn'll say
when I tell him
one of his gals is down here
stirring a fuss.
I ain't stirring no fuss.
I'm just here trying
to register to vote.
It's all right this time.
It's right
when I say it's right.
Recite the Constitution's
preamble.
Know what a preamble is?
"We the people
of the United States,
"in order to form
a more perfect union,
"establish justice,
"ensure domestic
tranquility,
"provide for
the common defense,
"promote the
general welfare..."
How many county judges
in Alabama?
(BREATHES DEEPLY)
Sixty-seven.
Name them.
JOHNSON: Aren't we done?
Are we not done with this?
Will this ever end?
I don't know,
Mr. President.
A comprehensive plan
is already in place.
The act was only passed
six months ago.
So hammer home that
impatience only hurts
the overall cause.
We're...
We're getting there.
Just... Just keep
reiterating the plan.
No, he doesn't
want reiteration.
He wants something
so he can say,
"Look, I told you
I had a dream
"and it's all coming
goddamn true,
"whether you like it or not!"
That's what he wants.
What he needs to do
is get on board
with what we're doing
instead of the other
way around. For once!
Mr. President, Dr. King.
KING: Mr. President.
Dr. King.
(CHUCKLES)
Well, I'll tell you.
I'm a tall son-of-a-bitch,
but this close to
the new Nobel laureate
and with all those
other trinkets
you've been collecting lately,
I feel tits-high
to a puppy dog.
Well, thank you,
Mr. President.
Mr. White.
Dr. King.
All right.
I'll tell you,
ending segregation,
proudest moment of my life
when I signed that '64 Act.
Proudest moment of my life,
I tell you.
Now civil rights
is a priority
of this administration
as you know.
Thank you.
We're gonna face
the challenge,
or this country is
storing up a heap
of trouble for itself.
Now, seeing as I can't
convince you to
work with
my administration
in an official capacity
inside the White House,
I feel damn fortunate
to have someone
as statesmanlike as you
leading the movement.
And I want you to go on
leading it. No one else.
Not one of these
militant Malcolm X types.
(CHUCKLING)
So... I wanna help.
Tell me how.
Well, Mr. President,
I'm here to speak
specifically
about the denial
of a basic American right
for the Negro citizen.
The right to vote.
Well, uh...
Technically...
Technically,
we already have it.
Yes, Mr. President.
But, we both know
in the South
black voters are
kept off the rolls
and out of
the voting booths
by systematic intimidation
and fear, Mr. President.
(CLEARS THROAT) Now,
you asked how you can help.
We want
Federal legislation
granting Negroes the right
to vote unencumbered.
And we want Federal
protocol eliminating
the decades-long dismissal
and illegal denial of
blacks seeking to vote.
And we want
robust enforcement
of that protocol.
Well, um...
(CLEARS THROAT)
That's fine.
But... Most of the South
is still not desegregating.
Let's not start
another battle
when we haven't
even won the first.
And you know what
the next battle should be?
The eradication of poverty.
I'm calling it
"The War on Poverty."
It's a matter
of political priorities.
Poverty is going to be
my focus at home
and I want you
to help me with this.
We can make big changes
in these things
for people of all colors.
And I know that
matters to you,
doesn't it?
This voting thing
is just gonna have to wait.
(CLEARING THROAT)
It...
(STAMMERING)
It can't wait, Mr. President.
Well, why not?
Because there have
been thousands
of racially motivated murders
in the South,
including those four girls.
Well, I know that...
And you know
the astounding fact
that not one
of these criminals
who murder us when
and why they want
has ever been convicted.
Yeah, I know we have a lot
of work to do down there.
Not one conviction
because they are protected
by white officials
chosen by
an all-white electorate.
And on the rare occasions
that they face trial,
they are freed
by all-white juries.
All-white because
you can't serve on a jury
unless you are
registered to vote.
Well, Dr. King,
you've certainly given me
something to think about.
But this administration
is going to set this
aside for a while.
Just for a while,
you understand.
Yes, Mr. President, I...
I understand.
(INDISTINCT CONVERSATIONS)
Selma it is.
Big speech lined up
for these folks tonight, Doc?
We need to see
what's what first,
Big Fellow.
We're just here
to test the waters.
Oh, my Lord.
What you got us into, woman?
We've got 128 miles
to come to our senses,
gentlemen.
NASH: Hush.
This here is the place
we need to be.
This right here
is the next great battle.
I can only imagine.
Hmm.
Decent-looking place
to die though.
(CHUCKLES WRYLY)
Ms. Nash.
Mr. Bevel.
Doc? This here is it.
Selma's the place.
A lot of groundwork
has already been laid
by the people here.
And they ready.
(INDISTINCT CONVERSATIONS)
(DOOR OPENS)
ORANGE: Sister Boynton.
BOYNTON: Mr. Orange.
Good afternoon.
MAN 1: Dr. King?
May I introduce myself?
Yeah, of course.
(GROANS)
MAN 2: Hey!
(PEOPLE CLAMORING)
It's okay. It's okay.
I'm okay.
This way, Dr. King.
KING:
That white boy can hit.
ABERNATHY:
This place is perfect.
What's the FBI's
current information
on Martin Luther King?
I heard he was
assaulted in Selma.
My information can be
summed up in a few words.
King is a political
and moral degenerate.
Well, you say that, J. Edgar.
I have to take it seriously.
But if he's a degenerate,
what I do know is,
he's a non-violent
degenerate.
And I want him
to go on leading
the civil rights movement,
not one of these
bloodthirsty militants.
What I need to know
right now is
what's he about to do next?
Mr. President,
you know we can shut men
with power down
permanently
and unequivocally.
I'm very aware of that,
Mr. Director.
Well, if you prefer
a different approach,
we can go with the wife.
We know there's tension
in the home already.
We can weaken the dynamic.
Dismantle the family.
(CHILDREN LAUGHING)
(PHONE RINGING)
Hello.
MAN: (ON PHONE)
You ain't got long.
When the hearts
of those Pickaninnies
of yours stop beating...
Same thing?
CORETTA: When are
you all heading out?
KING: We're heading back
to Selma at 5:00 a.m.
It turned out to be
an ideal staging ground.
There's a full
couple of weeks planned.
Quite a bit to be done.
I see.
That highway is nice now.
Get you there
in a couple of hours.
Good people
in those parts though.
Well...
I'm worried about the ones
who ain't so good.
This local Sheriff Jim Clark
is supposed to be
bad business.
Won't go down
without a fight,
they say.
And since we don't fight...
Well...
As good a place to die
as any, I guess.
I wish you wouldn't
talk like that.
It just takes the edge off.
You and your friends
can joke about that.
I don't joke about that.
You're right. I'm sorry.
I'll, uh, put these things
away in your bag now.
I didn't realize
you were leaving so early.
(SIGHS)
(PHONE RINGING)
Hello?
KING: (ON PHONE) Halie?
Martin.
I need to hear
the Lord's voice.
Oh.
Surely, Martin. Surely.
(JACKSON CLEARS THROAT)
JACKSON:
??Precious Lord
??Take my hand
??Lead me home
??Let me stand
??I am tired
(SIGHS)
??I am weak
??I am worn
??Through the storm
??Through the night
??Lord, lead me on
??To the light ??
(INDISTINCT CONVERSATIONS)
KING: Hey!
Hey!
Sully.
Look at you.
(LAUGHING)
Morning, Doctor.
Good morning, Doctor.
SULLIVAN: Drive all right?
KING: Good and long.
Good news is
Richie Jean is in there.
Oh, she's ready for you.
(ALL LAUGHING)
Negro, that's all
you had to say.
Uncle Marty!
There she is!
There's our girl!
Hey, Richie Jean!
RICHIE JEAN: Oh!
KING: Looking
like her mom.
You go play.
Hey!
Hey, Ralphy.
ABERNATHY: How you doing?
RICHIE JEAN: Hey!
Good to see you,
sweetheart.
Hey, come over here.
ABERNATHY: Oh, Lord,
it's good to see this!
Okay, now, I've got
the grits on the stove.
Uh, how many
we expecting today?
Well, now, Sister Jackson.
You know about our group,
the SCLC, right?
The Southern Christian
Leadership Conference?
A few of our top SCLC leaders
are with us this time
since we're going to
be here a little longer
than expected.
Now, this here's
Reverend C.T. Vivian.
He coordinates all
the SCLC branches.
Welcome.
Nice to meet you.
Welcome, welcome.
This is
Reverend James Bevel.
How you doing, ma'am?
I'm well. Thank you.
YOUNG: This here
is James Orange.
Oh, this is a big one.
I don't know if I've got
enough to feed you.
Well, let's find out.
How about that?
RICHIE JEAN: Hey!
(ALL LAUGHING)
Now, you got two of them
named James.
Oh, you can
call me Jim, Sister.
And Orange is
fine with me, ma'am.
Or Big Fellow!
All right. Well,
this is fine with me.
Mrs. Jackson.
Hosea Williams.
Or Castro!
Oh, yeah,
that's a long story.
Uh, those grits, they need
some stirring. Mind?
ABERNATHY: You put
your foot in it now.
Ain't you supposed
to be on a diet?
(ALL LAUGHING)
Somebody call Juanita.
There's a phone!
Hey, get off that phone.
Juanita?
ABERNATHY: Don't do it, Doc.
Don't do it...
(FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING)
Turning in, Doc.
You okay?
Yes, sir.
Good night to you.
Uh...
I wanted to tell you that
the students are in town.
Local students?
Oh, no.
The Student Non-Violent
Coordinating Committee.
Oh. Okay.
Our young friends at SNCC.
Mmm-hmm.
Good to know.
You the one
told them to organize.
Took it to heart.
Don't be surprised
if they don't give us
grief tomorrow.
Town folk may be happy
to see us. But SNCC?
They feel we're
in their territory.
They're young
and full of spirit.
Mmm.
Not a bad thing.
It'll sort out.
Good night.
"Boycotting the buses
in Montgomery.
"Segregation in Birmingham."
(APPLAUSE)
Boycotting the buses
in Montgomery.
Segregation in Birmingham.
(AUDIENCE AGREEING)
Now? Voting in Selma.
One struggle ends
just to go
right to the next
and the next.
If you think of it that way,
it's a hard road.
But I don't think
of it that way.
I think of these efforts
as one effort.
And that one effort
is for our life.
(AUDIENCE AGREEING)
Our life as a community.
Our life as a nation.
For our lives.
We can do this.
(AUDIENCE APPLAUDING)
We must do this!
We see children
become victims of one
of the most vicious crimes
ever perpetrated
against humanity
within the walls
of their own church!
They are sainted now.
They are the sainted ones
in this quest for freedom.
And they speak to us still.
They say to us,
to all of us,
all colors and creeds,
that we must do this.
They say to us
that it is unacceptable
for more than 50% of Selma
to be Negro
and yet less than 2%
of Negroes here
being able to vote
and determine their own
destiny as human beings.
They say to us that
the local white leadership
use their power
to keep us away
from the ballot box
and keep us voiceless.
(APPLAUSE AND AGREEMENT
CONTINUE)
As long as I am unable
to exercise
my constitutional
right to vote,
I do not have command
of my own life.
I cannot determine
my own destiny
for it is determined for me
by people who would rather
see me suffer than succeed.
Those that have
gone before us say,
"No more!"
AUDIENCE: No more! No more!
No more!
That means protest,
that means march,
that means disturb the peace,
that means jail,
that means risk!
And that is hard!
(SHOUTS OF AGREEMENT)
We will not wait any longer.
Give us the vote!
That's right! No more!
We're not asking.
We're demanding.
Give us the vote!
ALL: Give us the vote!
Dr. King. Roy Reed
of The New York Times.
Yes. Hello to you.
How are you?
I'm well, sir.
Thank you for asking.
Dr. King, are you
truly non-violent
if you are
provoking violence, sir?
We are here, using
our very bodies in protest
to say to those
who deny us...
Dr. King. Dr. King.
Pleasure, sir.
...that we will
no longer let them use
their billy clubs
in dark corners
and halls of power.
We make them do it
in the glaring light
of day, Mr. Reed.
Is SNCC standing with us
on this or not, gentlemen?
You want us to
bring our people in,
but you're not giving
anything in return.
Now we are asking for
some kind of commitment here.
Respectfully speaking,
of course,
we've been handling
the voter registration
in this town now
for two years.
Well, you haven't gotten
very far, have you?
Well, maybe not, Reverend.
But we're still here.
WILLIAMS: Meaning what?
FORMAN: This time next month,
you won't be!
WILLIAMS: That's insanity!
Just like you left Albany.
Those people are pathetic
down there now.
Like they daddy left home!
What we're trying
to explain is that
in Albany you all...
You know what I think?
Maybe we should
just leave Selma...
Now!
Leave it to these two.
Come back in
another two years
and see how much
further you got!
Sounds just fine to me.
KING: That's enough.
Enough of this now.
I haven't the time for this.
None of us
got the time for this.
John.
James.
The way our organization
works is straightforward.
We negotiate.
We demonstrate.
We resist.
And on our best days,
our adversary
helps the matter
by making a mistake.
Now, we were in Albany
for nine months
and we made
a lot of mistakes.
But their sheriff,
Laurie Pritchett,
he never made a mistake.
Kept his cool,
kept arresting us
in a humane way,
carried people to
the jail-wagons
on stretchers.
Day in, day out.
There was no drama.
You mean
there was no cameras.
Exactly.
Now I know,
we all understand,
that you young people
believe in working in
the community long-term.
Doing the good work
to raise black
consciousness.
It's good grassroots work.
I can't tell you
how much we admire that.
But what we do
is negotiate,
demonstrate,
resist.
And a big part of that
is raising
white consciousness.
And in particular
the consciousness
of whichever white man
happens to be sitting
in the Oval Office.
Right now, Johnson
has other fish to fry
and he'll ignore us
if he can.
The only way to
stop him doing that
is by being on
the front page
of the national press
every morning
and by being on the TV news
every night.
And that requires
drama.
Now...
John.
James.
Answer me one question.
I've been told
the sheriff in this town
isn't like Laurie Pritchett
in Albany.
He's a big ignorant bully
like Bull Connor
in Birmingham.
Well, you tell me.
You know Selma.
You know Sheriff Jim Clark.
Is he Laurie Pritchett?
Or is he Bull Connor?
He's Bull Connor.
ABERNATHY: Bingo!
Good.
That's good.
But it gets better.
See, Clark doesn't
control the streets
like Connor did in Birmingham.
Clark's the County Sheriff,
and all he controls in Selma
is the County Courthouse.
So relatively speaking,
we have clear avenues
of approach
to a defined battle zone.
(MUSIC PLAYING)
In the courthouse sits
the heart of the matter,
the voter registration office.
Now this is
an exceptional circumstance.
See, in Albany, there were no
clearly defined battle zones.
The issue was segregation,
and segregation
was everywhere.
In Selma, we can concentrate
our actions on one building.
A citadel,
defended by fanatics.
The Selma Courthouse.
A perfect stage.
(WHITE PEOPLE
SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY)
CLARK: Y'all deliberately
causing an obstruction!
You don't disperse,
you're gonna be arrested.
I promise you!
Sheriff Clark,
we're trying to gain access
to the registration office.
Which is our legal right.
There's too many of you.
And you know damn well
there is!
Now, y'all just gonna have
to wait at the rear!
No, Sheriff Clark.
We're going in the front
and we're gonna
wait right here.
Segregation is now illegal
in this country, sir.
(INDISTINCT SHOUTING
CONTINUES)
WOMAN: Get out, nigger.
JIMMIE: Come on.
CAGER: I'm trying.
VIOLA: Kneel down, Daddy.
CLARK: Come on.
Keep this sidewalk clear.
Clear a path!
Get out of the way!
Get the hell out of the way!
Keep the sidewalk clear!
I said keep it clear!
Okay. We about to sit
him down. He can't sit.
CLARK:
Then he needs to learn.
He gonna sit.
Sit down, God damn it!
JIMMIE: Hey, hey! Pa? Pa?
VIOLA: Daddy.
JIMMIE: I just told you
he can't sit.
CLARK: Oh,
what do we got here?
What's going on here, boy?
What we got here?
Jimmie! Sit down!
No, Mama, I'm sick of this.
Jimmie!
VIOLA: Don't do it.
Do you have a problem, boy?
JIMMIE: I'm sick of this!
I just told you...
CLARK: What'd you think, boy?
What'd you think?
What the fuck
are you thinking?
(INDISTINCT SHOUTING)
(BOTH GRUNTING)
(PEOPLE GASP)
Get that nigger woman!
MAN: Kill that nigger bitch!
Get your hands off of me!
(GRUNTING)
(PEOPLE CLAMORING)
(SCREAMING INDISTINCTLY)
WALLACE: We will not tolerate
a bunch of nigra agitators
attempting to orchestrate
a disturbance in this state.
Not as long as I'm governor.
Now, I stand here today
(CAMERA CLICKING)
in the cradle
of the Confederacy
to remind its people
of our Founding Fathers'
goals of duty.
Goals long since forgotten
by progressives and liberals
in favor of what they call
a changing world.
They seek to make us
one mongrel unit.
Instead of allowing
each race to flourish
from its separate
racial station
as has been the standard
for generations now.
Good morning,
Mr. President.
Their changing world
is sickening the balance
of the Southland.
Now...
I pledged to stand up
for Alabama when I campaigned
and the people elected me
on that pledge,
and that is exactly
what I intend to do.
(WOMAN SIGHS)
ABERNATHY: Johnson'll flinch.
KING: I'm tired, Ralphy.
Tiring of this.
Eyes on the prize, Martin.
Yeah, but what is
the prize, friend?
We fight to have a seat
at whatever table we want.
How does it help
a black man
to be able to eat
at a lunch counter
if he doesn't earn enough
to buy the burger?
Or worse yet,
can't even...
Can't even read the menu
'cause there was no Negro
school where he's from.
What is that?
That equality?
Amen.
And what about
in our minds?
Equality in the black psyche.
Look at these men.
Beaten and broken down
for generations.
Deciding to demand more?
What happens when
a man stands up and
says enough is enough?
Look at Medgar.
Murdered the man
in his own driveway.
Kids and wife right there
inside the house.
George and Herbert Lee,
Lamar Smith.
A man stands up,
only to be struck down.
And what happens
to the people he led?
(SIGHS)
What are we doing, Ralphy?
We take it
piece by piece.
Like we been doing.
We build the path as we can.
Rock by rock.
This cell
is probably bugged.
(LAUGHING)
It probably is.
Oh, Lord.
They're gonna ruin me so they
can ruin this movement.
They are.
"Look at the birds
of the air,
"that they do not sow,
nor reap,
"nor gather into barns,
"and yet your Heavenly Father
doth feed them.
"Are you not worth
much more than they?
"And who of you
by being worried
"can add a single hour
to his life?"
Matthew 6, verse 27.
All right.
Yes, sir.
(SIGHS)
VIVIAN: What?
Where did you hear that?
ORANGE: I overhead
them talking
about him coming in
this evening.
LEWIS: Overhead us?
I'm learning about this
just like you.
We didn't do this.
WILLIAMS: That Negro
can't be talking about that
"by any means necessary"
madness with these people.
They about to bust as it is.
He's on his way here,
right?
So we gotta
figure this out.
Right and fast.
Oh, he ain't on his way.
He here.
Holy shit.
(CAR DOORS CLOSING)
Are you all right?
(EXHALES)
I wish I had more time
to prepare is all.
I want to do this kind of
thing whenever possible.
But I don't get to
do it enough
to feel entirely
comfortable.
I prefer to be prepared.
Yes, I understand that.
I admire you. I do.
Sometimes I wish
I were more out there
in the trenches.
You do more than
you know, Mrs. King.
(EXHALES)
I'll tell you what
I know to be true.
It helps me in times
when I'm feeling unsure.
If you'd like.
Oh, please do,
Mrs. Boynton.
I know that
we are descendants
of a mighty people,
who gave civilization
to the world.
People who survived
the hulls of slave ships
across vast oceans.
People who innovate
and create and love
despite pressures
and tortures unimaginable.
They are in our bloodstream.
Pumping our hearts
every second.
They've prepared you.
You are already prepared.
Mrs. King, I mean
no disrespect.
I come with great respect
for your husband.
I have no army
behind me anymore.
I have myself and the truth.
That is all I stand on today.
You've said disrespectful
things in the past, Minister.
So you'll understand
why there is some
alarm here tonight.
I do. I understand that.
Your husband and I,
we do not see
exactly eye-to-eye
on how to achieve progress
for the black man.
And yes,
I have been piercing
in my critiques
of non-violence.
But because we don't agree,
Mrs. King,
does not mean
that I'm the enemy.
What do you intend to say
to these people then, sir?
A lot of work
has been done here,
and I don't intend to
see it undone tonight.
Let's just say,
my eyes see in a new way.
But your local sheriff here?
He doesn't know that.
So allow me to be the
alternative to your husband.
The alternative that
scares them so much
they turn to
Dr. King in refuge.
Let my being here, Mrs. King,
represent the factions
that will come if they don't
give the good reverend
what he's asking for and soon.
Do you know what he has said
about us in the past, Coretta?
He called us
"ignorant Negro preachers."
Called me
a modern day Uncle Tom.
Said on national television
that the white man pays me
to keep Negroes defenseless.
The white man pays me!
How could you allow it?
It wasn't like that
this time, Martin.
I'm telling you...
He spoke with some of
the words he's used before,
but it wasn't aimed at you.
It was...
It had more to do
with helping us.
Not that you need his help.
I'm just telling you
how it was.
This movement, our movement,
has been the one that
has moved the needle.
Our movement changes laws
and day-to-day life
for our people.
But what has he changed?
Actually changed?
You don't sound like yourself.
You sound tired.
And you sound enamored.
(CORETTA SIGHS)
I didn't mean that.
Corrie.
Coretta.
I didn't mean that.
(SIGHS)
I'm tired.
You're right.
Rest then.
Rest tonight, Martin.
WALLACE: This is not
what I want to hear.
How in Christ's sake does
Malcolm X slip into my state,
meet with the wife
of the other one,
and give an actual speech
to these nigras
who are already
riled up enough?
I mean, how does that happen,
Colonel Lingo?
Governor...
Is every spook militant
in existence
gonna pay us a visit?
Huh?
(SIGHS)
Do you know what this means?
Johnson is going to
get jumpy.
King and X together
is sending him
through the cotton-pickin'
stratosphere.
And pictures of nigras
getting beat in the street
doesn't help the matter.
Governor...
Now I can't make a move
against that backwoods,
white trash Sheriff Clark
'cause that'll be seen
as I'm helping King.
But somebody got to
get Jim Clark under control.
Election year is coming up
and this black voting
business won't abide.
I mean, what's not
clear about that?
Look, George,
I'm telling you,
if the Lord Jesus
and Elvis Presley
come visiting and they said,
"Jim, now, we need you to
treat them niggers nice."
Jim Clark would beat the shit
out of the pair of them,
then throw them in jail.
Jesus H. Christ.
Jim's a good old boy,
he's a friend of mine.
Jim Clark just ain't
that scary.
Now he's playing
into their hands.
Now...
If you want fear,
you need dominance in Selma.
Hoover picked up some intel
about a night march.
Wasn't announced.
It's some locals
outside of King's group.
Unofficial, they called it.
Supposed to happen
tomorrow night
once King leaves jail.
Going to some bleeding heart
fundraiser in California.
WALLACE: So...
King's out of town.
Fewer cameras.
And at night.
LINGO: Find a reason to
send us in there.
Let's scare some real sense
into them black bastards.
OFFICER: (OVER LOUDSPEAKER)
Y'all move back.
Move back now. Get back.
Go back to your homes now.
(OFFICER BLOWING WHISTLE)
(ALL SCREAMING)
Stop!
Leave him be!
Mama, come on!
We gotta keep moving.
Come on.
This way, this way.
WOMAN: Leave him alone.
(WOMAN SCREAMING)
(JAZZ MUSIC PLAYING)
(ALL PANTING)
It's all right.
It's gonna be all right.
Okay?
Act like you're...
Act like you're
reading your menu. Okay?
It's okay.
Pops...
It's all right, Mama.
It's gonna be cool.
It's okay, it's okay.
JIMMIE: Hey! Hey...
(PEOPLE SCREAMING)
No, get off of him!
Just get off of him!
Get off of him! No!
No! Get off of him!
(GROANS)
(VIOLA SCREAMING)
VIOLA: Stop it! No, no, no!
(COCKING GUN)
Stop it!
(VIOLA WAILING)
Help me.
(SIRENS BLARING IN DISTANCE)
(CRYING)
Help me.
Jimmie.
Jimmie. Jimmie. Jimmie.
Help me.
Sir?
Oh. Dr. King.
There are no words
to soothe you, Mr. Lee.
There are no words.
But I can tell you
one thing for certain.
God was the first to cry.
Yes.
He was the first
to cry for your boy.
Yes. I believe that.
Is your daughter...
Is Jimmie Lee's mother
here, Mr. Lee?
No, she...
She couldn't make it.
May I ask your age, sir?
Well, I...
I got 82 years.
1883.
Right.
(STAMMERING) Yeah.
Jimmie...
He born in '38.
He a Army man.
I mean, he was...
Was an Army man.
In the Army a spell.
He say, "Pa, you gonna vote
before you done."
Mmm-hmm.
That's what he said.
He tell me.
He was a good boy.
Yes.
Always good.
Jimmie gone.
I'm so sorry.
Yeah.
KING: Who murdered
Jimmie Lee Jackson?
Who murdered
We know a state trooper
acting under the orders
of George Wallace
pointed the gun
and pulled the trigger.
But how many other fingers
were on that trigger?
Who murdered
Jimmie Lee Jackson?
Every white lawman who
abuses the law to terrorize.
Every white politician
who feeds on
prejudice and hatred.
(ALL AGREEING)
Every white preacher
who preaches the Bible
and stays silent before
his white congregation.
(ALL AGREEING)
Who murdered
Jimmie Lee Jackson?
Every Negro man and woman
who stands by
without joining this fight
as their brothers and sisters
are humiliated,
brutalized, and ripped
from this earth!
(APPLAUSE)
When I heard
President Kennedy
had been shot and killed...
And when I heard
just yesterday
that Malcolm X,
who stood in this very church
just three weeks ago,
had been shot and killed,
I turned to my wife Coretta
and said the same thing
I often say
when one of our leaders
is struck down,
"Our lives
are not fully lived
"if we're not willing to die
for those we love
"and for what we believe."
(ALL AGREEING)
But today, Jimmie,
we're doing the living
and you've done the dying,
dear brother.
We will not let your sacrifice
pass in vain, dear brother.
We will not let it go!
We will finish
what you were after!
We will get
what you were denied!
We will vote and we will
put these men out of office!
We will take their power!
We will win what
you were slaughtered for!
PEOPLE: Yeah!
We're going back
to Washington.
We're going to demand to
see the President.
And I'm gonna tell him
that Jimmie was murdered
by an administration
that spends millions
of dollars every day
to sacrifice life
in the name of liberty
in Vietnam,
yet lacks the moral will
and the moral courage
to defend the lives
of its own people
here in America!
(APPLAUSE)
We will not let it go!
And if he does not act,
we will act. We will act!
We will do it
for all of our lost ones.
All of those,
like Jimmie Lee Jackson,
who have gone too soon,
taken by hate!
(APPLAUSE)
Let me hear
the top-tier issues
that have to be evident
in the overall
legislation we demand.
Let's break it down.
But let's root
this discussion
in what we know.
We know Johnson
can't see the full picture.
So, let's paint it for him.
What are the specific
hardships and humiliations
we can address
within the larger
context of legislation?
Doc, we gotta start with
banning these laws that
if a Negro tries
to register,
I mean,
actually musters up
the courage to go
in that courthouse,
that their name and address
is published in the paper.
It gives anybody who wants
to do them any harm
their exact location,
and we know how the Klan is.
I hear that.
But the poll taxes
got to be our focus first.
'Cause black people are poor!
Black people
are poor down here.
Yep.
BEVEL: And they expected
to pay for every year
they weren't
legally registered
before they can register.
Now, what the hell is that?
Who got that kind of money?
(ALL CLAMORING)
VIVIAN: Come on now!
Listen now!
The big issue is
voting vouchers.
Is that the number one issue?
VIVIAN: Now hold on.
Let me finish.
'Cause everybody'll forget
about this part.
But if you're Negro,
the only way you can vote
is if an approved registered
voter vouches for you.
Right? So, let's say,
you take some place
like Lowndes County,
where there are no Negroes
who are registered
and you've got to have
someone who is registered
to vouch for you.
What are you supposed to do?
Hmm?
Mmm.
Nobody you know,
not a single black person
for 100 miles is registered.
So how do you
get the voucher, right?
To get you into
the courthouse door
to pay the poll tax
to get your name published
and get yourself dead.
That's true.
We need a new plan!
I can't take him
back to Washington
and waltz into the White House
with a list of empty demands.
Tactics, my friends!
We must break down
this institution
into the tangible
tactics that it takes
to dismantle it.
JOHNSON:
What's your next move?
A march from Selma
to Montgomery
to protest and amplify.
Well, I'll be damned.
This was always
part of the plan,
wasn't it?
Provoke some tragedy
in little old Selma,
then go big.
Get someone killed and
march on the State Capitol!
Selma to Montgomery's
gotta be 50 miles!
You march those people into
rural Alabama unprotected,
it's gonna be open season.
It's too damn far
and too damn dangerous!
Then propose
new legislation, sir.
I can't do that this year.
I won't! I told you.
We need your
involvement here,
Mr. President.
We deserve your help
as citizens of this country.
Citizens under attack.
Now, you listen to me.
You listen to me.
You're an activist.
I'm a politician.
You got one big issue.
I got a hundred and one.
Now, you demanding more
and putting me on the spot
with this visit, that's okay.
That's your job.
That's what you do.
But I am sick and tired
of you demanding
and telling me
what I can
and what I can't do.
If you want my support
on this voting thing,
I need some quid pro quo
from you.
What do you want,
Mr. President?
We have a line on
some threats that are, uh,
particularly troubling.
Well, what's new?
No, no. This is serious.
Credible threats with detail.
RUSTIN: This information,
coming from the FBI,
I assume?
High-level?
The same high-level
that's been tracking us
like animals?
Bugging our homes
and our hotel rooms.
Digging for things that
simply are not there, Lee?
This all feels
very convenient.
WHITE: Okay.
This is coming from
Lowndes County, Alabama.
Between Selma and Montgomery.
I'm telling you,
if he were my guy,
I'd keep him
off the frontlines.
Just for a while.
Not gonna happen, Lee.
Meet me halfway
on this, Martin.
I can't, Mr. President.
Can't or won't?
I came here hoping
to talk to you
about people.
People are dying
in the street for this.
It cannot wait, sir.
Mr. President,
how did it go?
What can I do to help?
Get me J. Edgar Hoover.
MAN 1: (ON TAPE) King,
you know
you are a complete fraud
and a liability
to all nigras.
Like all frauds,
your end is approaching.
You are done.
Your degrees and your fancy
awards will not save you.
The American public
will soon know you
for what you are,
an evil, abnormal beast.
(MAN 2 GRUNTING ON TAPE)
(WOMAN MOANING ON TAPE)
(TAPE STOPS)
That wasn't me.
That isn't me, Corrie.
I know.
I know what
you sound like.
I've gotten used to a lot.
All the hours
wondering after your safety,
worried about how you are.
This house.
Renting here.
No foundation.
Without the things
the children should have,
all because of
how it would look.
I have gotten used to it,
for better or worse.
(SIGHS)
But what I have
never gotten used to
is the death.
The constant closeness
of death.
(SIGHS)
It's become like
a thick fog to me.
I can't see life sometimes
because of the fog of death
constantly hanging over.
People actually say that
they will stop the blood
running through the hearts
of our children.
That's what they said on the
other end of that phone line.
How they're going to
kill my children.
And what they'll do to you
and how they'll do it.
How many years have I
had to listen to this?
The filth,
deranged and twisted
and just ignorant enough
to be serious.
If I ask you something,
will you answer me
with the truth?
Yes.
Good,
because I am not a fool.
Do you love me?
Yes, I love you, Coretta.
(SNIFFLES)
Do you love
any of the others?
No.
I need to put the march
back a day.
YOUNG: Why?
I have to be
home right now.
YOUNG: Oh.
Yes. Okay. I understand.
But I have to tell you
the organization looks good.
Real good.
The mood is strong.
And the locals are prepared.
The SNCC kids are ready to go.
We can start it off
from Selma,
and you can join in
on the second day.
I just think it'd be a mistake
to hold people back
when their blood is up.
KING: I hear you,
but we need to be out there
full throttle.
This ain't a test run.
We need to get to Montgomery.
I warned Johnson that
we were going to the Capitol.
We need to do just that.
YOUNG: And I believe we will.
We'll get there.
And when we do the real deal,
the finale,
when you make the big speech
at the end,
right on Wallace's doorstep.
KING: I don't know, Andy.
YOUNG: It'll be just fine.
We'll get it started strong.
And you'll finish strong.
Mmm.
Okay. Uh... Let's proceed.
But only one of us
walks to start.
I don't want to
get back on Monday
and find all
our leadership in jail.
One of us walks.
YOUNG: Understood.
There will be no march
from Selma to Montgomery.
It is not conducive to
traffic flow on Route 80.
Or to public safety.
Your lives could
be in danger,
but we're going to be strong
if we stick together.
Don't fight back.
It's a non-violent movement.
Non-violence is not passive.
It's actually very strong.
We shouldn't
do this, John.
This is not us.
This is not SNCC.
It's some bullshit.
It's gonna do more for King
and the SCLC than for Selma.
This is Alabama.
They can keep their asses
in Washington, D.C.
You don't tell us
how to live our lives.
This is an example of what
you might deal with out there.
What you might experience.
Here we go. Let's show them.
We don't want
your kind here.
Go to the bottom
of the river, black boy.
We're going to put you down
in Alabama River!
LEWIS: He's not even here.
How's it gonna
do more for him?
FORMAN: Well, why ain't
he here, then, man?
Are you listening
to yourself?
First, it's gonna
do more for him.
Now, it's why
he ain't here?
Do you want him here,
or do you not want him here?
Honestly, I don't
give a rat's ass
about that man.
That's your hero.
Let's take these bastards
and stick them down
into Alabama River
and never see them again.
James, you are
so off-base with this.
All this nonsense.
This ain't what
SNCC is about.
Don't make me out to be
the bad guy here, John.
I'm not! You're the one
playing me small.
Don't demonize me...
(OVERLAPPING ARGUMENT)
You're mad because
they called him in.
We were here first.
And they called him in.
I get it. I understand that.
But if we are really
and truly for the people,
and the people of Selma
chose him,
well, then the people
have spoken.
And if they want to march,
then I'm marching with them.
Then, brother,
you're marching
as John Lewis.
Not as part of SNCC.
It's been voted on
and decided.
For this march,
you're on your own
with De Lawd
and his disciples.
(INDISTINCT CONVERSATIONS)
VIVIAN: Short man wins.
Short man wins.
All right.
All right. Who got it?
It's on you, Hosea.
WILLIAMS: You ready,
young blood? You ready?
All right. Let's do this.
All right.
REED: About 525 Negroes
had left Brown's Chapel
and walked six blocks to cross
Pettus Bridge
and the Alabama River.
There were young and old,
and they carried
an assortment of packs,
bed rolls
and lunch sacks.
The troopers were waiting
300 yards beyond
the end of the bridge.
Behind the troopers
were dozens of possemen,
15 of them on horses,
and perhaps
100 white spectators.
Can you swim?
Not many swimming pools for
black folk where I come from.
Yeah.
(REPORTERS CHATTERING
INDISTINCTLY)
(CAMERAS CLICKING)
Andy, it's Bayard.
Everybody there?
Yes.
BAYARD: Turn on CBS
right now, Andy.
Right now.
You have a TV there?
Yes. Now?
Right now!
Turn on the television set.
ANNOUNCER ON TV: We interrupt
this program to bring you
a special bulletin
from CBS News.
Give 'em two minutes.
Stand right there.
We're ready.
This is an unlawful assembly.
You have two minutes
to disperse.
Go home or go to your church.
This march will not continue.
Two minutes.
May I have
a word with the Major?
There's no word to be had.
Major Cloud,
may we speak with you?
Troopers, advance!
(GUNSHOT)
(TROOPERS YELLING)
(PEOPLE SCREAMING)
(PEOPLE SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY)
Seventy million people
are watching this.
REED: The first
10 or 20 Negroes
were swept to the ground
screaming,
arms and legs flying,
packs and bags went skittering
across the grassy divider.
(GUNFIRE)
(ALL SCREAMING)
(GROANING)
REED: Those still
on their feet retreated.
A cheer went up
from the white spectators
lining the south side
of the highway.
(ALL SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY)
(COUGHING)
Come on.
You gotta come on.
Please, don't...
REED: The troopers
continued pushing,
using both the force
of their bodies
and the prodding
of their nightsticks.
(GROANS)
(ALL CLAMORING)
(GUNSHOT)
REED: Suddenly, there was
a sharp sound, like a gunshot,
and a gray cloud spewed over
the troopers and the Negroes.
But before the cloud
hid it all,
there were several seconds
of unobstructed view.
(CLEARS THROAT)
(YELLING)
REED: Fifteen or 20
nightsticks
could be seen through the gas,
flailing at the heads
of the marchers.
Ahhh!
REED: The Negroes cried out
as they crowded together
for protection,
and the whites on the
sidelines whooped and cheered.
From the hospital
came reports of victims
suffering fractures of ribs,
heads, arms and legs.
And Negro leader John Lewis,
despite injury from
a possible skull fracture,
led the marchers
back to the chapel
after the encounter
with officers.
Help!
He said, "I don't see
how President Johnson
"can send troops to Vietnam
"and can't send troops
to Selma, Alabama."
To which the Negroes present
roared their approval.
(GOSPEL MUSIC PLAYING)
(INAUDIBLE)
MAN: Gerry! Gerry,
come with us! Come with us!
We need your gun, man!
GERRY: I can't walk!
MAN: Come with us.
We know you got them
guns in the shed, Gerry.
Hey, hey, hey,
what you need guns for?
The Bible says,
"An eye for an eye," Reverend.
Yeah?
I'm sick of this shit!
How many guns
you think they
got down there?
That's an entire army
down there.
What you got? A couple
of .32s? A .38?
Maybe a couple
of old scatterguns? What?
I got enough
to kill a couple
of them crackers,
that's what I got!
And how many of us you think
they gonna kill
in retaliation?
With their 12-gauge
pump-actions,
their Colt automatics,
their Remingtons, their
helicopters, their tanks!
We won't win that way,
and I ain't talking
about the Bible.
I ain't talking
what's right by God.
I am talking facts.
Cold, hard facts!
Now, you take two of them,
and they take 10 of us.
No. We have
to win another way.
ANNOUNCER: (ON TV) ...to our
regularly scheduled program.
We're going
back to the bridge.
We're going to finish this,
we promise you that,
Ms. Amelia.
We go again.
(REPORTERS CLAMORING)
(CAMERAS CLICKING)
MALE REPORTER: Dr. King!
Can we get a statement, sir?
Dr. King! Morning, Doctor.
Can we get
a statement, please?
Morning.
While rageful violence
continues
towards the unarmed people
of Selma,
while they are assaulted
with tear gas
and batons
like an enemy in a war,
no citizen of this country
can call themselves blameless,
for we all bear
a responsibility
for our fellow man.
I am appealing to
men and women of God
and goodwill everywhere,
white, black and otherwise.
If you believe all are created
equal, come to Selma.
Join us. Join our march
against injustice
and inhumanity.
We need you to stand with us.
GRAY: Judge Johnson,
Dr. King's call-to-action
was nationally televised.
We've seen hundreds of people
travel across the country
to attend tomorrow's march,
mostly white,
mostly clergy of some kind.
The SCLC is seeking
a federal court order
enjoining
the state authorities
from interfering
with the next march.
You're asking me to overturn
the Governor's mandate
and to do so
without a hearing,
but it's not
going to happen at all
without a proper proceeding.
Dr. King is in position to
lead tomorrow's march, Judge.
Understood, but you will have
your day in court
on Thursday, Mr. Gray.
Meanwhile, there will be
no march tomorrow.
I will not oppose Wallace
against protocol.
"Thousands head south
in moral crusade."
WHITE: The SCLC
already filed an appeal
against Wallace's orders
this morning.
You want my advice,
Mr. President?
You have to ask?
Give King
the march to Montgomery.
Do that, and
then Selma's over.
Then you're back in control.
In control of what?
Another civil war?
This ain't about
the goddamn march.
You think he cares
about the march?
He wants
the law changed, now.
I've got Congress
calling me by the dozens.
I've got picketing that gets
bigger and bigger every day.
He tugs on their goddamn
white liberal conscience.
Every march pulls 'em.
Especially when
people are getting
beat up in the streets.
These pictures are
going around the world, Lee.
I understand, Mr. President.
All the more reason
to act now.
I'm gonna act now.
You tell Wallace
and those backwater hicks
I don't want to see any more
of this horseshit.
And you tell King he best not
march, you hear me?
Either King stops
and Wallace stops,
or I'll stop 'em both.
I'm here on
the President's order
to try and make this work.
Please work with me.
So we give up the march
and you...
You give what?
We asked
for federal protection.
And with no disrespect,
but when the
Assistant Attorney General
is the highest-ranking
federal official in Selma,
we have our answer.
And it's not the one we want.
Might I suggest that you
speak with Governor Wallace
and Sheriff Clark
and urge them
against violence
instead of trying to
persuade us
not to have
a peaceful protest?
Maybe we can make a deal.
What if I
could assure you
that the administration
would endorse a later march
if tomorrow is called off?
You know what?
He's closer than you may think
to coming around
on this issue.
I believe this compromise
might be agreeable.
KING: Mr. Doar?
Thousands have gathered here
to demonstrate their dignity.
I don't want to
challenge Judge Johnson.
I don't want to go
against the President.
I don't want any of this.
The President could stop this
with a stroke of his pen.
He chooses not to.
The decision
is with your side, sir,
not ours.
(BLUES MUSIC PLAYING)
Good to see you, Father.
Good to see you.
Thank you for coming.
Thank you for coming out.
Hello, sister. Good to
see you this afternoon.
Oh. Oh... You came.
You called
and we came, my friend.
You are not alone, my friend.
Welcome, welcome.
Hi, what's your name?
Susan.
Hi, I'm Viola.
Welcome to Selma.
Yes, ma'am, I'm good.
How are you?
Fine, thank you.
What is your name
and where are you from, sir?
My name is James Reeb.
I've come from Boston.
Tell me, why have you
traveled here, Mr. Reeb?
I heard about the attack
of innocent people
who just want their rights,
and I couldn't
just stand by
when Dr. King put out
that call to clergy.
I couldn't.
The President doesn't
want us to march today.
(CROWD CHEERS)
The courts don't want
us to march.
But we must march.
ALL: Yeah!
We must stand up.
We must make
a massive demonstration
of our moral certainty.
(CROWD CHEERING)
I'm so glad
we're here together today.
I thank you for standing up.
For we shall be victorious
in our quest.
We shall cross the finish line
hand in hand.
For we shall overcome.
All right.
(APPLAUSE)
(FOLK MUSIC PLAYING)
Troopers, withdraw!
(APPLAUSE)
My point is, after
what happened the last time,
if it don't feel right, we
don't do it. That's my point.
We've been going round
and round on this for hours,
and nothing's gonna
change the fact that
it was Doc's decision
and we have to support him.
NASH: This is a movement
of many, not of one.
So any choice we make
has to be right for many.
Come on, Diane.
Now, you know
that's not what I meant
by that, all right?
People are angry, Dr. King.
Angry. They went
back to that bridge
because they were
hot about Sunday.
That was our moment
out there today.
And you threw it away.
They could've sealed off
the road behind us.
No food, water, no kind of
support allowed through.
We wouldn't
have made 10 miles.
You saying this was a trap?
(SIGHS)
I don't know what it was.
That was no trap!
You know why they
opened up the road to us?
Because all them nice,
respectable white folks
was with us, and we
should've capitalized on that.
Because they're not gonna be
around here for long.
They never are!
It was Martin's call.
It's done.
He made the wrong
goddamn call!
Hey, watch your mouth,
young man!
Two days ago,
you didn't wanna
march at all.
And now you're mad because
it didn't go the way
you planned?
Calm down, brother.
Now, what happened
out there today?
You gotta tell us something.
Please.
I'd rather people be upset
and hate me
than be bleeding or dead.
(SIGHS)
KING: My dearest Corrie,
at a time when I need you,
I cannot call you.
And I have done this
to myself, to us.
At this late hour,
my thoughts are of you
and all you have sacrificed
for this struggle.
So many have sacrificed.
So many have been lost.
I wonder how many
must we lose.
I pray for discernment and
guidance as we journey on.
I pray, too,
that I can justify
the faith you once had in me.
I, too, often feel that heavy
fog you spoke of, Corrie.
Only you and our family
clears the haze.
Love, Martin.
MAN: He betrayed trust.
He called, we came, and he
didn't fulfill his own call.
Yeah, but sometimes
it's not that clear-cut.
Sometimes it's instinctual.
Like when you're preaching,
and you're just flying.
You know,
you're not on the notes.
You're not on memory.
You're tapped into
what's higher, what's true.
God is guiding you.
I've known that feeling.
It's rare,
but I've known it.
(BOTH CHUCKLE)
I think that's
what happened to Dr. King
up there on the bridge today.
He kneeled down,
prayed to God
and got an answer.
And he was brave enough
to follow that answer,
and I, for one,
don't fault him for it.
Except he owes me
a bus ticket home.
(CHUCKLES)
MAN 1: You know what
I hate more than niggers?
MAN 2: What's that?
White niggers.
Look, we don't
want trouble, okay?
MAN 1: No, you came here
stirrin' trouble.
(GROANING)
(GRUNTS)
Doc,
someone's been hurt.
(GROANING)
A priest, from Boston.
White.
Now you know what
being a nigger
around here
feels like, boy.
Hurt? How?
Dead.
(GASPS)
I need a phone!
Chicago, Detroit, Boston,
I don't care.
Hell, you got 2,000 people
marching up in Harlem.
Well, good for you.
But when you have people
come inside the White House?
Inside the White House!
On a tour?
They just sat down, Martin.
They sat down
in the main corridor,
started singin' and shoutin'.
Well, I won't have it!
I cannot stop
people from expressing...
You can! You can stop them.
No, you can stop it.
You, sir, can do more.
Now I'm glad to hear that you
called Reverend Reeb's
widow, sir.
That is very fine,
and it is right.
I only wish that
Jimmie Lee Jackson's family
would have received
the same consideration
from their President.
Don't you lay your guilt
at my door.
You're the one
choosing to send
people out to slaughter when
we told you there was trouble.
We won't sit idle
while you wait
another year or two
to send this bill up
at your leisure.
That should be clear by now.
We will continue
to demonstrate
until you take action, sir.
And if our President
won't protect our rights,
we will take
this fight to court.
You know, I'm...
I'm trying here.
We're getting close
to figuring something out
on this voting thing,
but I will not have this!
This bill has been
almost impossible to craft,
you hear me?
You think you're jugglin',
Martin? I'm jugglin', too.
I am a preacher from Atlanta.
You are the man
who won the presidency
of the world's
most powerful nation
by the greatest landslide
in history four months ago.
And you are the man
dismantling your own legacy
with each passing day.
No one will remember
the Civil Rights Act.
But they will remember
the standoff in Selma
when you never even
set foot in this state.
They will remember you saying,
"Wait," and "I can't,"
unless you act, sir.
KING: Evenin'.
Evenin'.
(MUSIC PLAYING ON RADIO)
I wanted to speak privately.
I know there's been trouble
with the group,
and I apologize
that our efforts
have caused a rift
between y'all.
That's a painful thing,
I know,
and I'm truly sorry
it's happened.
Yeah, painful.
(SIGHS)
LBJ is not moving, John.
I thought he would, but
our efforts are not working,
and I can't risk another march
with people getting killed
when it's not working.
I won't do it.
We need voting,
not marching.
You know that.
We have to move
beyond these protests
to some real political power.
This can't go on forever
like this.
I can't go on like this.
(SIGHS)
When I was...
When I was working with SNCC
on the Freedom Rides,
the Montgomery bus
reached the city limits.
We got off.
And out of nowhere,
from all directions,
they came.
There was men, women.
Kids, too.
They had just about
every makeshift weapon
you could think of.
I mean, bats, bricks,
tire irons, pipes.
I remember...
I remember this little girl
just clawing her nails
into the side
of my friend Jessie's face
while her daddy... Her daddy
beat him with an ax handle.
Jessie was unconscious,
and they just kept beating
on him and beating on him.
I must've passed out
on the asphalt somewhere.
Next day, I found myself
patched up
and sitting in a church.
I could barely
hold my head up,
but I needed to be there.
You were gonna be speaking.
And I needed to hear you.
And I was feeling down,
but you got up there.
You remember that day at all?
(SIGHS)
I don't think we remember it
the same way.
What'd I say, John?
I'm about to tell you
right now.
And I hope you hear me.
You said
that we would triumph.
That we would triumph
because there could be
no other way.
And you know
what else you said?
You said,
"Fear not.
"We've come too far
to turn back now."
KING: I feel good
about where we are.
We have a strong case.
We can do this.
Right.
KING: Now, Ms. Cooper
and Ms. Boynton are here,
and they need to be ready.
LEWIS: Mmm-hmm.
KING: A lot depends on
what they have to say. Okay?
YOUNG: Mmm. I hear
what you're saying, but...
You're here.
Yes, I'm here.
I'm glad.
Just in time.
In the matter of
the Southern Christian
Leadership Conference
v. the state of Alabama,
I will now hear testimony
from the plaintiffs. Mr. Gray.
Your Honor, you will hear
testimony from the victims
who were beaten and bludgeoned
in their quest for freedom.
For their right to vote
and to self-determine.
The fact of the matter,
Your Honor,
is that the incidents that
occurred cannot be disputed.
These particular circumstances
will paint
a thorough picture
of the horrific events
endured in Selma.
Very well, you may proceed.
Mr. King, you went out
on that bridge
in direct violation
of that judge's orders.
You deliberately
disobeyed this judge
and the Governor,
did you not?
Thousands of people
came to Selma,
aroused by Sunday's
brutal acts
exacted by officials
of the city of Selma
and the state of Alabama.
I felt if I had not
led the march,
pent-up emotions
and inner tensions
would have led to
an uncontrollable
retaliatory situation,
a violent situation
on both sides.
I don't need any of your
preaching and prancing
in here,
you hear?
I want an answer.
Objection.
Watch it, counselor.
I'm trying very hard, Judge.
Try harder, counselor.
It seems basic to
our constitutional principles
that the extent of
the right to assemble,
and demonstrate and march
along the highway
in a peaceful manner
ought to be commensurate
with the enormity
of the wrongs
that are being protested
and petitioned against.
In this case,
the wrongs are enormous.
Therefore,
the extent of the right
to demonstrate
in an estimated five-day march
from Selma to Montgomery
has been approved accordingly.
MAN: Yes!
WOMAN: Thank God!
(CROWD MURMURING)
JUDGE: There's no further
business with this court.
These proceedings
are concluded,
with our thanks
to the litigants.
Good day, gentlemen.
(INDISTINCT)
MAN: Yeah, that's right.
Well, now, we don't like
to have no mistakes, if you...
If you're sure about it.
Bayard says that Harry says
he can get Nina Simone,
Dick Gregory, Joan Baez,
Peter, Paul and Mary in.
(PEOPLE EXCLAIMING
IN SURPRISE)
Come on now.
We don't got
money for that.
Well, Harry is chartering
a plane himself.
??Day-O, day-O
ALL:
??Daylight come
and me wan' go home ??
President's angling
for your blocking
of the march
to be overturned.
Unfortunately, all my
maneuvers have been
put on hold
while the matter's
being adjudicated.
JOHNSON: Governor,
you wanted to talk.
Well, Mr. President...
Malcontents are
disrupting Alabama,
and it's your responsibility
to stop them.
They're protesting about
the right to vote
and the way they're treated
in your state.
So that's your problem,
your responsibility,
and it's on your watch.
Mr. President, I disagree.
We have a certain way things
are done. It's the way it is.
And it's the way
the people want it to stay.
George, why
are you doing this?
Your whole career
has been working
for the poor.
Why are you off
on this black thing?
Well, 'cause you can't
ever satisfy them.
First, it's the front seat
of the bus.
Next, it's take over
the parks,
then it's the
public schools,
then it's voting,
then it's jobs,
then it's distribution
of wealth without work.
George, you seen
all those demonstrators
out front of
the White House
keeping my Lady Bird awake
the whole damn night?
Oh, yes, Mr. President.
I saw them.
Well, let's go out there,
you and I,
and announce that
you've decided to let
the blacks vote undeterred,
and this whole mess
will go away.
And I don't have to draft
bills or force the issue.
Now, why don't
we do that, George?
Why don't you just
let the niggers vote?
You agree they got the right
to vote, don't you?
Oh, there's no quarrel
with that.
I know that.
That's the law.
Then why don't you
just let 'em vote?
I don't have that power.
It belongs to
the county registrars.
Now, don't shit me
about who runs Alabama.
I don't have
any legal power
over the county registrars,
Mr. President.
They have their regulations
and they adhere.
Are you trying to shit me,
George Wallace?
Are you trying
to fuck over
your President?
Mr. President...
We shouldn't even
be thinking about 1965.
We should be thinking
about 1985.
You and I'll be
both dead and gone by then.
In 1985, what do you
want looking back?
You want people
remembering you sayin',
"Wait," or "I can't,"
or, uh, "It's too hard"?
I don't right care
what they think,
and you shouldn't neither.
Well...
I'll be damned
if I'm gonna let history
put me in the same place
as the likes of you.
I speak tonight
for the dignity of man
and the destiny of democracy.
At times, history and fate
meet at a single time
in a single place.
So it was last week
in Selma, Alabama.
There, long suffering
men and women
peacefully protested
the denial
of their rights as Americans.
Rarely in any time
does an issue lay bare
the secret heart
of America itself.
The issue for equal rights
for the American Negro
is that issue.
For this issue,
many of them
were brutally assaulted.
There is no Negro problem.
There is no Southern problem.
There is only
an American problem.
(POLITICIANS APPLAUDING)
The Constitution says that
no person shall be kept
from voting
because of his race or color.
To correct the denial
of this fundamental right,
this Wednesday,
I will send to Congress a law
designed to eliminate
these illegal barriers.
The bill will strike down
voting restrictions
in all elections,
federal, state and local.
And we shall do this.
We shall overcome.
(APPLAUSE)
We believe we can cover you
through Lowndes County,
but once we add
the final day's march
through Montgomery,
and you're passing through
all those tall buildings
and whatnot,
coverage becomes challenging.
So please consider
driving in on the final leg.
And please consider nixing
the speech at the Capitol.
Well, if Wallace
will see us
when we arrive,
there'll be no need
for a speech.
(CHUCKLES)
Can you arrange that?
I can't hide.
We can't hide.
You understand.
I don't want to see this
go wrong for you.
Don't you want
to protect yourself, Doctor?
Let me try to do that.
You know, I know you
want to live to see
the fruits of all this work.
I know you do.
I'm just asking
you to allow us
to help you do that.
I'm no different
than anybody else.
I want to live long
and be happy.
But I'll not be focusing
on what I want today.
I'm focused on
what God wants.
We're here for a reason,
through many, many storms.
But, today,
the sun is shining,
and I'm about to
stand in its warmth
alongside a lot of
freedom-loving people
who worked hard
to get us here.
I may not be with them
for all the sunny days
to come,
but as long as there
is light ahead for them,
it's worth it to me.
Thank you, John.
(FOLK MUSIC PLAYING)
(INAUDIBLE)
(CROWD CHEERING)
KING: We heard them say
we'd never make it here.
We heard them say
they'd stop us,
if it was the
last thing they did.
We heard them say
we don't deserve to be here.
But today,
we stand as Americans.
(CROWD CHEERING)
We are here,
and we ain't gonna let nobody
turn us around.
This mighty march,
which will be counted as
one of the greatest
demonstrations
of protest and progress,
ends here in the
Capitol of Alabama
for a vital purpose.
We have not fought only
for the right to sit
where we please
and go to school
where we please.
We do not only strive here
today to vote as we please.
But with our commitment,
we give birth each day
to a new energy
that is stronger than
our strongest opposition.
(CROWD CHEERING)
And we embrace
this new energy so boldly,
embody it so fervently,
that its reflection
illuminates a great darkness.
(CHEERING)
Our society
has distorted who we are.
From slavery
to the Reconstruction
to the precipice
at which we now stand,
we have seen powerful
white men rule the world
while offering poor white men
a vicious lie as placation.
And when the poor
white man's children
wail with a hunger
that cannot be satisfied,
he feeds them
that same vicious lie.
(CROWD AGREEING)
A lie whispering to them
that regardless
of their lot in life,
they can at least be
triumphant in the knowledge
that their whiteness makes
them superior to blackness.
But we know the truth.
We know the truth, and we will
go forward to that truth,
to freedom.
(CHEERING)
We will not be stopped.
We will march for our rights.
We will march to demand
treatment as full citizens.
We will march until the
viciousness and the darkness
gives way
to the light of righteousness.
(CHEERING)
No man, no myth,
no malaise
will stop this movement.
We forbid it. For we know
that it is this darkness
that murders the best in us
and the best of us.
Whether Jimmie Lee Jackson
or James Reeb,
or four blameless little girls
struck down
before they had even begun.
You may ask, when will we
be free of this darkness?
I say to you today,
my brothers and sisters,
despite the pain,
despite the tears,
our freedom will
soon be upon us.
(CROWD CHEERING)
For "truth crushed to earth
will rise again."
When will we be free?
Soon, and very soon.
Because you shall reap
what you sow.
When will we be free?
Soon, and very soon.
Because no lie
can live forever.
When will we be free?
Soon, and very soon
because "Mine eyes have seen
"the glory of the coming
of the Lord.
"He is trampling out
the vintage
"where the grapes of wrath
are stored.
"He hath loosed
the fateful lightning
"of his terrible swift sword.
"His truth is marching on.
"Glory! Hallelujah!
"His truth is marching on."
(INSPIRATIONAL SONG PLAYING)
(WORKERS IN SELMA SINGING
TRADITIONAL HYMNS)